Kollisch, Margaret; Papers ger051
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Margarete Kollisch Papers
1910-1979
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Kollisch, Margarete, 1893-1979
ger051
0.3 cubic ft.
The collection contains published and draft writings of Margarete Kollisch, and correspondence with Dr. Albert Einstein and other notables.
Biographical History
Margarete Moller was born on December 9, 1893 in Vienna, Austria. After studying modern philology at the University of Vienna, she completed her teaching certificate in 1917 and worked as a teacher, translator and journalist, while still in Europe.
Margarete married Otto Kollisch in 1923 and they had three children, two sons and a daughter. In 1939, the Kollisch family emigrated to the USA, where Margarete received a massage therapists license, and worked for twenty-five years in that field. She also taught French and German and worked for a time in a used-book store. She lived in Staten Island, NY until her death in 1979.
A prominent author in her native German language, she wrote poems, prose and short stories, and fairytales for children. Her work appeared in many Austrian and German newspapers and journals, and she read her poetry at the Austrian Institute, Austrian Forum and the Social Scientific Society, as well as on radio programs in New York and Vienna.
She was honored for her literary achievements both in Austria and the United States. She was a member of the Alpenlandischen writers group in Europe, and in 1969 received the medal for foreign language writing from York College.
As a refugee of World War II Europe, Kollisch often wrote of the political turmoil of war, especially as it related to her home, Vienna. Being old enough to remember the First World War, she was able to draw comparisons and comment on the European condition.
Kollisch, who had a unique understanding of the human perspective, wrote about the role of women in society, and liked to use personal relationships as themes for her poetry. Her daughter, Eva, was an especially important influence.
Scope and Contents
The Margarete Kollisch Papers consist of copies of published books from Bergland Publishers and the Osterreichische Verlagsanstalt (the Austrian Publishing House), as well as typed drafts of poetry and other writings in German, English and French. Also included are copies of correspondence with Dr. Albert Einstein, and other notables such as Dr. Emil Staiger of Zurich.
Researchers of German emigre literature will find this collection of interest, as will anyone interested in women authors.
Additional Kollisch materials can be found at the Leo Baeck Institute, New York City, and at the Oesterreichische Exilbibliothek, Literaturhaus, Vienna. The Leo Baeck Institute has all the published work of Kollisch, copies of most stories and poems, and some original manuscripts. The Oesterreichische Exilbibliothek, Literaturhaus has all the published work of Kollisch, a few original pieces, and some copies of stories and poems.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged cby format.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Eva Berliner-Kollisch, daughter of Margarete Kollisch. 1981 December
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Literature; Women authors; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Correspondence; Fairy tales; Poems; Short stories; Kollisch, Margarete, 1893-1979; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
- Brief biography written by the author, Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 1)
- Bibliography of published works, taped interviews, and secondary sources where the author is mentioned, compiled by the authors daughter, Eva Kollisch, Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Einstein, Albert, 1934; Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Staiger, Emil, Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 4)
- Fairy Tales, "Billy the Parakeet", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 5)
- Fairy Tales, "Tiny and the Halloween Ghosts", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 6)
- Fairy Tales, "The Little White Crib", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 7)
- Fairy Tales, "How the Pansy Got Its Name", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 8)
- Fairy Tales, "The Little Fairy Who Got Into Trouble", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 9)
- Fairy Tales, "Tony and the Ferry-Boat", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 10)
- Fairy Tales, "The Happy Life of Al the Alarm Clock", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 11)
- Stories, "Wachtmeister Wallenstein", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 12)
- Stories, "Dreiklang", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 13)
- Stories, "Valse Macabre", 1963 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 14)
- Stories, "Valse Macabre", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 15)
- Stories, "Onkel Doktor", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 16)
- Stories, "Das blassrosa Abendkleid", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 17)
- Stories, "Der Fremde", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 18)
- Stories, "Die Maninka", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 19)
- Gedichte/Poems, pp. 1-78, 1910-1942 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 20)
- Gedichte/Poems, pp. 79-140, 1944-1953 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 21)
- Gedichte/Poems, pp. 141-189, 1954-1968 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 22)
- Gedichte/Poems, pp. 190-231, 1969-1979 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 23)
- "Lob der Kochkunst oder wie man Manner fesselt", 1929 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Prolog im Himmel", ca. 1930 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "3 Geburtstagsgedichte fur Onkel Stohr", 1930 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Mit unseren ersten Kirschen", 1931 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Meinem Lehrer Professor R. F. Arnold gewidmet. Demselben zum 60. Geburtstag.", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Mondsee", 1932 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Ins Gaestebuch von Pension Antoinette", 1934 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Aus unserem Gaestebuch fuer Marjorie Noble, Canada", 1932 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Zirkus Stohr", 1933 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Mit selbstgebackenen Busserln zum 60. Geburtstag", 1934 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Aus einem Briefwechsel in Reimen", 1935 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Antwort auf die Marienbader Epistel", 1936 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Badner Kille-Marsch", 1937 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Affidavit-Foxtrot", ca. 1938 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Answer to Mr. circaG. Kolffs Invitation", 1941 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Eine Neubearbeitung der Osterreichischen Volkshymne", 1942 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Milk Farm Song", 1942 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Indiana Marsch (nach O, du mein Oesterreich)", 1943 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Der Autor", 1947 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Wiener Sonntagsausflug 1906", 1952 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Fur Stohrs Gastebuch", 1953 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Reise um die Welt in 84 Tagen", 1954 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Merry Christmas in the Wood", 1956 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "From one Car to the Other", 1957 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Circle: We want to hear the truth we want to hear", 1962 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Lime-rick", Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Der Umweg", 1962 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Leichtes Gepack", 1963 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Den Vertraumten", 1963 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Fur eine Siebzigjahrige", 1963 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "To Senator R.F.K.", 1966 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Der Fremdling", 1972 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "The Ballad of the Waterbug", 1973 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "From a Limousine to a Volkswagen", 1974 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- "Wiener Empfang von "Osterreichisches aus Amerika", 1974 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 24)
- Betrachtungen, Aphorismen, Epigramme, 1910-1979 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 25)
- "About Professional Smiles", 1974 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 26)
- "Company", 1974 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 26)
- Ruckblendung: gedichte und prosa, Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 27)
- Book, Wege und Einkehr: ausgewahlte gedichte. Wien: Bergland Verlag, 1960 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 28)
- Book, Unverlorene Zeit: ausgewahlte gedichte und betrachtungen. Wien: Osterreichische Verlagsanstalt, 1971 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 29)
- Book, Ruckblendung: gedichte und prosa. Wien: Bergland Verlag, 1981 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 30)
- Copyright information provided by Eva Kollisch, Undated (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 31)
- Book Review, Article by Gert Niers: "Vollendung der spatromantischen Lyrik" New York Staats Zeitung und Herold, 1975 June 21/22 (Box 1 (Margarete Kollisch Papers), Folder 32)